This is Lawrence Sperry
aviation pioneer andcertified daredevil.
He's about to fly his plane past a group of judges
at the Paris AviationContest.
All of a sudden
his assistant climbsout onto the wing of the aircraft
causing it tosuddenly veer to the right.
Instead of correctingit
Lawrence takes his hands off the controls
and miraculously,
the plane steers itself back oncourse.
This is a real photo of that exact moment.
On the next pass
Lawrence himself climbs out onto the other wing
and the plane continues to
flyperfectly straight past the judges.
Sperry hadinvented the world's first autopilot.
Oh, and itwon him the competition.
By taking a gyroscope andconnecting it
to the plane's rudder and elevators,
the gyroscope would command
the controls to keepthe plane completely level.
Using a gyroscope inthis way
was an engineering breakthrough
And itwent on to be used in everything
from cars, ships, rockets
all the way to today's phones.
Over thecourse of 100 years
all of this technology wascondensed
down into a tiny chip just 1 mmwide.
And because of this
your phone knows its positionin space at all times.
But how does this work?
The basic principle of a gyroscope
is that if youspin a disc really quickly,
its angular momentumtries to keep it perfectly stable.
By placingthe disc in a
three-axis gimbal with very littlefriction,
everything else will move around it,
butthe disc will stay locked in place.
By measuring how much the
gimbals have moved relative to thedisc
you can accurately measure
how much theobject has rotated.
Engineers in the 20's began
torealize how useful this could be
and gyroscopeslike this started
to appear in ships, rockets, andwarplanes,
just like the ones you can use in WarThunder.
War Thunder is a free-to-play
large-scalemultiplayer military action game
where aircraft,ground vehicles, and naval vessels
fight indynamic battles
at locations around the world.
War Thunder recreates the
scale and intensityof battles
using a wide range of iconic machines
and lesser known prototypes
spanning from the mid-20th century to the present day.
In War Thunder
all advanced military technologies are available.
Guided missiles, active protection systems,
night vision devices, and even a
nuclear strikethat can flatten the entire map.
The detail of War Thunder's damage model is insane.
Disable atank's tracks and it will immobilize them.
Shootout a plane's fuel tank and it will ignite.
Therecent update, Sky Odyssey,
features a wide range of new vehicles
including Greek fighter jetsand Indonesian tanks.
It also has new modes anda brand new arena
for combined battles betweenair and ground vehicles.
Download War Thunderfor free
on PC, PlayStation, and Xbox
by using thelink in the description.
All new players
and those who haven't played
War Thunder for half a yearor more
will receive some special bonuses.
Youcan also immerse yourself in
the exciting battlesin War Thunder mobile.
Download it for free on iOS
or Android using the link in the description.
Inthe midst of World War II,
Nazi Germany came outwith this, the V2 rocket.
This was a long rangemissile designed
to strike major cities from upto 200 m away.
It was one of the first advancedrockets ever built,
and it was guided by a pair ofgyroscopes
similar to those used on Spar's plane.
During the flight, these would
keep the rocket on a planned trajectory,
and when the rocket reacheda certain speed,
it would cut off its engines
andfall ballistically onto its target.
But in orderfor this to work
it had to know how fast it wasgoing.
In another part of the guidance system,
it used a very basic accelerometer
to measurechanges in speed.
This was essentially just aspinning disc
with a weight added to one side.
The disc could tilt around this axis
and the wholeunit was on a platform
that could rotate aroundthe vertical axis.
When the disc was up to speed
it would keep it and the weight locked in place.
But when the rocket accelerated,
the weight wouldwant to stay where it is
due to Newton's FirstLaw of motion.
This would add a force to the disc
causing it to tilt over.
As we know, if you try totilt a fast spinning gyroscope,
it will cause itto rotate around the vertical axis.
This is calledprecession.
The rocket's acceleration would causethe disc to tilt
and in turn the whole gyroscopewould precess.
The more the rocket accelerated
the more the gyroscope would precess.
And so, by measuring exactly how much it precessed
theonboard computer
could measure its acceleration.
By accumulating all of the acceleration
measurements over time,
the current speedof the rocket could be calculated.
It was a geniussystem,
but in practice, it didn't work very well.
The V2 was inaccurate
often missing entire citiesby up to 10 m.
Over time, the small amount
offriction on each gimbal built up
and graduallycaused the gyroscope to drift off course.
Thisproblem plagued gyroscopes for decades.
But nomatter how smoothly they were made,
there wasno way to completely remove the friction.
Thatwas until they invented this.
the ring laser gyroscope.
With these, there were no moving parts.
A laser would emit a beam of light
via a system ofmirrors onto the same light sensor.
Under normalcircumstances
the beams of light would
travel the exact same distance
and hit the sensor at theexact same time.
Since both beams have the exactsame frequency,
they would show up perfectly insync.
But if the gyroscope rotates,
one beam oflight will have to travel
a slightly greaterdistance than the other one
and will therefore arrive slightly later.
The sensor would pick thisup
as a slight shift between the two frequencies.
The more the object rotated,
the more out ofphase the two frequencies would be.
These ring laser gyroscopes
were a major breakthrough inaccuracy
and they could be made much smaller
than mechanical gyroscopes.
Throughout the 80s
they started being used in
everything from rockets to airplanes,
replacing the old mechanicalgyroscopes.
But as technology developed
the need for an even smaller gyroscope grew,
andthat's where we are now.
This tiny little thing isa MEMS device.
It takes all of the concepts of theoriginal gyro
and compresses them down
onto a chipjust 2 mm wide.
Inside, it's made up of severalsmaller parts
three accelerometers and three gyroscopes,
one for each axis.
The intricatedetails that
detect the movement are so small
that a bacteria could easily fit between them.
Tosee it working in action, you need a microscope,
but we don't have one, so here's an animation.
First, let's look at how the accelerometers work.
Each one is made up of two main parts.
At thecenter
there is a structure with sensing fingers
that allows it to move back and forth.
This sitsneatly inside a fixed structure
that also hassensing fingers, but cannot move.
Together, thesetwo parts form a capacitance
which is picked up bythe sensing fingers.
When the object acceleratesin this direction
the central structure will wantto stay where it is,
just like the mass in the V2rocket.
If we zoom into the sensing fingers
thecapacitance here will go down
and the capacitancehere will go up.
The more the object accelerates,
the more it will affect the capacitance.
Bytaking the data from all three accelerometers
and plotting it over time,
the phone's computercan
figure out its movement in 3D space.
For thegyroscopes, things are a little bit trickier.
Aseparate part within the central structure is made
to constantly oscillate back
and forth at an exactfrequency.
Sensing fingers on the outside
measure the capacitance,
which should form a constantwave.
When the object rotates around this axis
it causes two parts at the center
to tilt outin opposite directions.
This is much easier to understand
if we look at a simple tuningfork
with both sides vibrating in sync.
If we start to rotate the tuning fork
like this, thanks to the coriolis effect,
it pushes each fork out in opposite directions.
Inthe gyroscope,
the rotation of the object causes
the inner section to tilt in opposite directions.
When these sections move
the resonant frequencyof
the structure changes slightly.
This slightchange is picked up by the sensing fingers
as aslightly lower or higher frequency.
When all axesare combined together
the phone's computer can
calculate its exact orientation in space.
Perhapsnothing shows the last century of technologicalevolution more than these gyroscopes.
Thanksfor watching
and I'll see you in the next video.